<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Bowden in Cheshire, April 6th, 1691 at the funeral of the right honourable Mary, Countess of Warrington by Richard Wroe.</title>
            <author>Wroe, Richard, 1641-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67185</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3729</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12196</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12931300</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12931300</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95677</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67185)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95677)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 995:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Bowden in Cheshire, April 6th, 1691 at the funeral of the right honourable Mary, Countess of Warrington by Richard Wroe.</title>
                  <author>Wroe, Richard, 1641-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.M. for R. Clavell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Warrington, Mary Booth, --  Countess of, d. 1691.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95677:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95677:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at <hi>Bowden in Cheſhire, April 6th.</hi> 1691. AT THE FUNERAL Of the Right Honourable, MARY Counteſs of <hi>Warrington.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>RICHARD WROE,</hi> D. D. AND Warden of <hi>Chriſts College</hi> in <hi>Mancheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> for <hi>R. Clavell</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church Yard,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:95677:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Alſton, <hi>R. P. D.</hi> Hen. Epiſc. <hi>Lond.</hi> à Sacris.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Maii, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:95677:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Honourable, HENRY, EARL of</hi> Warrington, <hi>and Lord Lieutenant of the</hi> County Palatine <hi>of</hi> Cheſter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF an Averſeneſs to appear in Print, and a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious Fear of expoſing my ſlender Performances to publick View, might have pleaded my Excuſe, I had not troubled <hi>your Lordſhip</hi> with an Addreſs of this Nature. But ſince <hi>your Lordſhip</hi> will have me Publiſh what I would much rather had been kept private, I hope <hi>your Honour</hi> will pardon my prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Your Name to that which claims a Right to Your Patronage, and I am ſure wants your Protection.</p>
            <p>In Paſſions of Grief, (eſpecially of Affectionate Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row) things are at once more eaſily, and more deeply impreſs'd on our Minds; and when the Affections are warm, they ſoon entertain a Fondneſs for that which is grateful to them. I have reaſon to ſuſpect ſome of my Auditors of ſuch a kind Partiality, and too fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable a Repreſentation of what they heard delivered upon that unwelcome Occaſion, which might byaſs <hi>your</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:95677:3"/> 
               <hi>Lordſhip</hi> into a good Opinion of, and a Deſire to ſee, what a Paſſionate Concern, and Surprizing Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row would not allow you to hear.</p>
            <p>This makes me lay it at <hi>your Honours</hi> Feet with an entire Submiſſion to the Reſult of your Judicious Peruſal, and better Thoughts; having no other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in tendring it to Your View, than to teſtifie my willingneſs to comply with <hi>your Lordſhips</hi> Requeſt, and a readineſs to pay any Service that I am capable of rendring to <hi>your Self,</hi> or <hi>Right Honourable Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which I reckon my ſelf moſt happy in, is the Opportunity I have hereby of acknowledging the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations I have to the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Dunham,</hi> and the Reſpect I always found from that obliging Generoſity, which ſeems Hereditary to Your <hi>Family,</hi> of which I ſhall always covet to be thought a true Honourer, and hope <hi>your Lordſhip</hi> will Accept this Small Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of my Gratitude, and believe me to be what I ſincerely am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Much Obliged and very Humble Servant, Ric. Wroe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95677:3"/>
            <head>A <hi>Funeral Sermon</hi> Preached at Bowden in Cheſhire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>HEB. vii. 25.</bibl>
               <q>Wherefore He is able alſo to ſave them to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt that come unto God by him, ſeeing He ever liveth to make Interceſſion for them.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Words being recommended at the Requeſt, and I doubt not on the inward Senſe and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction that the <hi>Right Honourable Perſon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceas'd,</hi> found in her Reflexions on them, need not my ſlender Apology for the Choyce of them. And were <hi>we</hi> as feelingly acquainted with the Import of them, and had as fully digeſted them in our retired Thoughts, as <hi>ſhe</hi> had, we ſhould find them more ſuitable to the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, than they may ſeem to be at firſt View, and ſhould reliſh ſuch a Sweetneſs in the ſaving Truths they contain, as would at once raviſh our Affections, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95677:4"/> them with deſire to endear them to the Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of others.</p>
            <p>For they contain the Great Ground of our Title to Happineſs, the ſure Anchor and firm Foundation of our Hope, which is bottom'd on the great Worth and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of our <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> his Ability to <hi>ſave to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt</hi> all that lay hold on him by a lively Faith; which to them that do ſo, becomes the joyful Evidence of that Intereſt and Aſſurance, which creates a ſolid Satisfaction, an inward Joy and Conſolation, rejoycing in the Merits, and triumphing in the All<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſufficiency of ſuch a Saviour, as is able <hi>to ſave to the uttermoſt all that come unto God by Him, ſeeing he ever liveth to make Interceſſion for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Happy is that <hi>Soul</hi> that relying on his Saviours All-ſufficiency, can rejoyce in a ſence of its Intereſt in him: Bleſſed is that <hi>Faith</hi> that is founded on this <hi>Rock of Ages, One mighty to ſave</hi> (in the Prophets Character of him) to whom we may cheerfully truſt our Salvation, and need not fear, and ſhall not be aſhamed: Happy is that <hi>Mind</hi> that can repoſe its Confidence in a full and firm Perſwaſion of the Salvation purchaſed by its All-power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Saviour: Pleaſant are thoſe Reflexions which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany a Life of Faith, which over-looks this preſent State, and (with St. <hi>Stephen)</hi> ſees Heaven it ſelf opened, <hi>and</hi> Jeſus <hi>ſtanding at the Right Hand of GOD,</hi> ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thoſe that depend on him, into thoſe Manſions of Glory, where he is now continually interceding for them: Happy ſhall we be, if the Conſideration of our Saviours Fullneſs engage our Obedience to him, and enflame our Deſires and Affections after him, ſo as to commit our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95677:4"/> Souls to him in well-doing, and truſt him with the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of them, through a full Aſſurance of the Suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of his <hi>Merits,</hi> and the prevalency of his <hi>Interceſſion.</hi> Now that we may be thus affected, ſhall be the Deſign of my Diſcourſe; and ſhall think my ſelf happy, if our Meditations on theſe Words may have the ſame Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon us, which I doubt not they had on <hi>that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Perſon,</hi> that left them for the preſent Subject, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſirous that others ſhould reap the ſame ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that <hi>She</hi> found in them. In order whereunto, I ſhall briefly run over the Severals of the <hi>Text,</hi> and then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to apply it to the Inſtructions of Wiſdom and ſeaſonable Application.</p>
            <p>The Words are part of one of the Seven Arguments, wherewith the Apoſtle in this Chapter magnifies and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alts the Sacerdotal Office of Chriſt, above that of the <hi>Aaronical</hi> Prieſthood. This Sixth Argument begins at the 23<hi>d.</hi> Verſe, <hi>And they truly were many Prieſts, becauſe they were not ſuffered to continue by reaſon of Death; but This Man, becauſe he continueth for ever, hath an unchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Prieſthood:</hi> As if he had ſaid, the <hi>Levitical</hi> Prieſts were <hi>Mortal,</hi> but Chriſt is <hi>Immortal;</hi> they were conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> but he abideth <hi>for ever,</hi> and therefore hath a better, becauſe an <hi>unchangeable Prieſthood:</hi> And becauſe he hath ſo, therefore he is able <hi>to ſave to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt,</hi> ſince he never fails to prevail for thoſe for whom he intercedes, and he never ceaſes to intercede for thoſe that come to God by him, <hi>ſince he ever liveth to make Interceſſion for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95677:5"/>
            <p> The main Point then in the Text, <hi>is the Aſſertion of Chriſts All-ſufficiency for the Work of our Salvation,</hi> back'd with a <hi>Two-fold Reaſon;</hi> the <hi>One</hi> drawn from the Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municableneſs of his Prieſthood, the <hi>Other</hi> from the laſt Act of it, which is his Interceſſion: To which I ſhall add what is here alſo expreſt, <hi>The Qualification of thoſe that receive the Benefit of his Interceſſion, they muſt be ſuch as come to God by him:</hi> That as the one is the great Ground of our <hi>Faith,</hi> ſo the other may become the ſure Anchor of our <hi>Hope and Confidence,</hi> that we do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume for Salvation by him, till we apply our ſelves to him for it, and by Faith lay hold on the Merits of his Death, and the Prevalency of his Interceſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The All-ſufficiency of Chriſt in the Work of Man's Salvation, is the great Thing here aſſerted. <hi>He is able to ſave to the uttermoſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Phraſe is Emphatical, and may denote either <hi>ad perfectum</hi> (as ſome render it) the Compleatneſs of the Salvation wrought by him; or <hi>in perpetuum</hi> (as others) the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manency and Perpetuity of it; or elſe the Perfection of his Influence in working out ſo mighty Salvation for us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Salvation he wrought for us, is every way complete and perfect.</hi> He ſaves from the loweſt degree of Sin and Miſery, to the higheſt Pitch of Glory and Happineſs: He delivers us from all Evil, and ſets us beyond the reach of it: He delivers us from the hands of our Enemies, and he exalts us in Triumph over them: He leaves no thing unaccompliſhed, that can be reckoned any tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95677:5"/> to, or part of, our Salvation: <hi>Whatever good Work he has begun, he will perform and finiſh it,</hi> Phil. 1. 6. <hi>He will ſtabliſh us in the Faith,</hi> and at laſt make Faith per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and conſummate, <hi>being the Author and Finiſher of it,</hi> Heb. 12. 2. <hi>He makes Men ready to every good word and work, and preſerves their whole ſpirit, ſoul and body blameleſs to his coming,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5. 23. And then he will improve Grace into Glory, and ſummate the Happineſs already commenc'd in endleſs Fruition: Which is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Notion of the Phraſe, and denotes;</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>The Permanence and Perpetuity of his Salvation.</hi> The Purchaſe he made for us, is of an Inheritance <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in the Heavens, incorruptible, and undefiled, that fadeth not away:</hi> His Kingdom is an everlaſting Kingdom, that has no Bounds, and knows no End. <hi>He ſaveth to the uttermoſt,</hi> that is, for ever, than which nothing can be more, or rather, beyond which nothing is. Other Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours and Deliverers hath God raiſed up for his People, but for a Time onely; but he made his Son an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Saviour, <hi>He ſent him to purchaſe Eternal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption for us,</hi> Heb. 9. 12.</p>
            <p n="3">III. His <hi>ſaving to the uttermoſt,</hi> may denote <hi>the power of his Influence, the perfection of all his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakins in the work of our Salvation.</hi> Whatever was to be done, he alone was able to do it; whatever he undertook to do, he perfected and finiſhed it. Was there a Price to be paid? He laid down his own Life, a moſt valuable Purchaſe, a precious Ranſome. Were there Enemies to be ſubdued,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95677:6"/> which required Power and Authority to effect it? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him ſat down on the Right Hand of the Majeſty on high, inveſted with all Power both in Heaven and Earth. Do we need daily Pardon and Favour from God? Behold him continually interceding for us with the moſt efficacious Oratory of his Blood and Merits, preſenting that before his Father, and by Vertue of that Meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Oblation reconciling him to us. Thus he ſaves all manner of ways, by all manner of means: Nothing is wanting to our Salvation, nothing can be done to make it more complete and perfect. And all this the Apoſtle here confirms by a double Reaſon;</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Uncommunicableneſs of his Prieſthood (in the Verſe foregoing) <hi>this Man hath</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Sacerdotium nunquam tranſiturum, <hi>that cannot paſs away, that does not deſcend from Father to Son;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranſibile, <hi>ſuch as paſſeth not from him to any other;</hi> which is as much as to ſay, <hi>ſuch as has no Succeſſor in his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatorial Office,</hi> he being the only yet withal eternal Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, <hi>and therefore is able to ſave to the uttermoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From his continual Interceſſion, which is the laſt Act of his Prieſthood, <hi>he ever liveth to make Interceſſion for us.</hi> There are Two Parts, or Offices of Chriſt's Prieſthood, the one of offering up himſelf a Sacrifice on the Croſs, the other, his appearing before God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and there preſenting the Merits of that Blood and Sacrifice, which is his interceding for us. We read, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. 3. <hi>Another Angel came and ſtood at the Altar, having a Golden Cenſer, and there was given unto him much In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, that he ſhould offer it with the Prayers of all Saints</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:95677:6"/> 
               <hi>upon the Golden Altar.</hi> The Angel is Chriſt, the Incenſe his own Prayers in Heaven, which he continually puts up when the Saints pray on Earth, and ſo perfumes all their Prayers, and procures all Bleſſings for them; and ſo St. <hi>John</hi> names both theſe together, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 2. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him at once, <hi>our Advocate, and the Propitiation for our Sins,</hi> which make up the Two Parts of his Office; the one, the great Act of his Prieſthood on Earth, when he offered up his own Blood on the Croſs <hi>with ſtrong Crying and Tears,</hi> Heb. 5. 7. The other is his continual Employment in Heaven, where having brought that Blood into the Holy of Holies, he there inceſſantly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers it up, that is, preſents it before his Father, as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Atonement and full Propitiation for the Sins of Men, and by Vertue of that Oblation, prays or intercedes for them.</p>
            <p>Now great is the Force of the Apoſtles Reaſon, to prove his Ability <hi>to ſave to the uttermoſt, ſeeing he ever liveth to make Interceſſion:</hi> For he dyed to merit our Salvation, but he ever liveth actually to confer it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that come to God by him. If he had not lived again by his Reſurrection, <hi>(whereby he was decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be the Son of God with power,</hi> Rom. 1. 4.) or if he had revived but for ſome time onely, and not for ever, we had not been raiſed from our Sins, nor Death perfectly ſubdued: But ſince we can affirm with St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 6. 9. <hi>That he being raiſed from the dead, dyeth no more, death hath no more Dominion over him;</hi> ſince he liveth for ever, we may ſtrongly argue with the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>If when we were Enemies, we were</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:95677:7"/> 
               <hi>reconciled to God by the Death of his Son, much more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reconciled, we ſhall be ſaved by his Life.</hi> If he being riſen, was able to exalt himſelf to a Life glorious and immortal, we have proof ſufficient of his Ability, <hi>to ſave to the uttermoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet the ſtrength of the <hi>Argument</hi> lyes not in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing riſen to Life, but in his <hi>living for ever to this end that he may intercede for us.</hi> For others beſides him, ſhall live for ever: Angels are immortal, and the Saints ſhall ſurvive to Eternal Ages, yet both of them are ſo far from being able <hi>to ſave to the uttermoſt,</hi> that they could neither Purchaſe Salvation for themſelves, nor others. The Higheſt Angel in Heaven could not Redeem ſo much as one of their own Laps'd Tribe, nor all the Celeſtial Hierarchy, the whole Angelick Order, ſave any of the fallen Angels. The greateſt Saint in Glory could not ſo much as <hi>Redeem his own Soul, or give to God a Ranſom for it.</hi> But 'tis his Sole Prerogative whoſe proper Office it is to intercede, and who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lives for ever that he may execute an Eternal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, the Conſummation of which Conſiſts in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion at the Throne of Grace.</p>
            <p>Now that we may better apprehend the manner, and Efficacy of <hi>his interceſſion,</hi> I ſhall briefly point at the Method and Order, as well as the Power and Prevalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of it. Neceſſary then it was that Chriſt having made an Oblation on earth to Appeaſe offended Juſtice, ſhould have ſomething alſo to preſent before the face of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Heaven: For otherwiſe by the Apoſtles Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he had not been a Compleat Prieſt, Heb. 8. 4. <hi>if</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95677:7"/> 
               <hi>he were on Earth, he ſhould not be a Prieſt, i. e,</hi> if he had ſtaid ſtill on Earth after the Sacrifice of himſelf, he had not been a perfect Prieſt, he had left his work imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, he had not fullfill'd the part of an Interceſſor, which was to be the laſt Act &amp; Conſummation of his Prieſt-hood. For in this he was to anſwer to his Type the High Prieſt, who without entring into the Holy of Holys, was not a perfect High Prieſt; for, to offer there, was the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and peculiar Act of the High Prieſthood. And ſo it was our Saviours Office to enter into Heaven, and there become our Advocate, as before he made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Propitiation for us (as the Apoſtle concludes the Argument,) Heb. 8. 1. <hi>We have ſuch an High Prieſt who is ſet on the right hand of the Throne of the Majeſty in the Heavens,</hi> viz. to preſent this his Sacrifice before the Mercy-Seat, which is the peculiar Office and Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of his Glorious Prieſthood. This is what the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calls <hi>his appearing in the preſence of God for us,</hi> Heb. 9. 24. Namely, when we are Summoned before the Tribunal of Juſtice, there to anſwer the Charge laid againſt us, then he appears as our Advocate, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to his Father the Merits of that Oblation, which he made of himſelf as a full ſatisfaction to his Juſtice, which tho' offered but once, yet does remain for ever before the Mercy-Seat, and is continually offered up by him who continues a Prieſt for ever.</p>
            <p>And all this he does as <hi>a publick Perſon,</hi> preſenting himſelf in our Nature, and in his own, as a <hi>Mediator</hi> between God and man, as a Pledge and Surety for us: And he preſents his own Merits as a publick ſatisfaction
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95677:8"/> to the Juſtice of God for the debt of Sin, as a publick price for the Redemption of Mankind: All which being offered to the Father by the Son of his Love, in whom he is well pleaſed, and who appointed him to this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, cannot fail of making a powerfull interceſſion on our behalf for all that his Meritorious ſufferings for us did deſerve, either for the Expiation of Sin, or the purchaſe of Salvation.</p>
            <p>Now this is neceſſary to be obſerv'd, to manifeſt the falſity of that diſtinction Coyn'd in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> between <hi>Mediators of Redemption and Interceſſion,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to maintain the Invocation of Saints and Angels, who may therefore (ſay they) be pray'd unto, becauſe they intercede to God for us.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe they do pray for us, (which yet we are not abſolutely certain of, the Scripture having no where told us ſo, and the great Service of Glorifyed Saints con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting rather in Anthems of Praiſe, than in Requeſts and Prayers) but allowing that they do pray for us as an Effect of their <hi>Charity,</hi> (which we know remains there, and is no doubt in an high meaſure extended to the Members of the Church Militant) yet that may be done with Relation to the State of the Church in general, whoſe welfare they wiſh and pray for, as an Expreſſion of their Charity, not as an Act of their Office to Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate for particular perſons. For where are they Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized to ſuch an Office? Or can we imagine them to run before they be ſent (as ſome in the Church Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant do) or take to themſelves that Honour without being called of God, without a ſpecial Deſignation to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95677:8"/> ſuch an high Employment? No ſure; 'tis part of their Glory, and the great Matter of their Joy to behold their Saviour fulfilling that laſt Act of his Prieſtood in Heaven, who onely can intercede, becauſe he alone has Merits to preſent whereby to ſupplicate before his Father. For he that is an <hi>Advocate</hi> muſt be a <hi>Propitiation</hi> too; and we know we have ſuch <hi>an Advocate with the Father,</hi> but we know no other; and he that can intercede, muſt be able alſo <hi>to ſave to the uttermoſt;</hi> but who dare give that Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Angels or Saints which belongs ſolely to Chriſt, <hi>through whom alone we have boldneſs and acceſs with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence by the Faith of him,</hi> Eph. 3. 12. If Faith in him be the Ground of our Confidence, ſhall we apply our ſelves to any other in whom we have not believed? Where the Apoſtle ſeems as if he deſigned to obviate that common Plea of theirs, <hi>that being ſo unworthy of our ſelves, we are to make our Addreſſes by the Courtiers of Heaven, who are more in favour with God:</hi> More than we indeed, but not more than his Son, whom the Father has commiſſioned to preſent our Services to him, and will accept none but ſuch as make their Applications by him; for ſo the Text ſays, <hi>He is able to ſave to the uttermoſt thoſe that come to God by him.</hi> Which leads to the next thing in the Words;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Qualification of thoſe that receive the Benefits of his Interceſſion, they muſt be <hi>ſuch as come to God by him, i. e.</hi> believe in him, and rely on him; as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God is frequently explain'd in Scripture. Our Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. <hi>He that cometh to God muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95677:9"/> 
               <hi>that he is.</hi> And he that cometh to God for Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, muſt bring Chriſt with him, relying by Faith in his Merits, and ſupplicating in the efficacy of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Interceſſion. So when Chriſt invites <hi>all that are weary and heavy laden to come to him,</hi> St. Mat. 11. 28. he calls for our Faith in him, which then becomes truly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving when it brings the Soul to God by him. No com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God but by Faith, for <hi>without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe him;</hi> no Faith is acceptable to the Father but in and through his Son, in whom alone he is well pleaſed. They are Strangers to the Covenant of Grace, that look for Pardon of Sin by any other means than through the Blood of Chriſt: They know not what Salvation is that hope to obtain it by any other Name, than his that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed it, ſince <hi>there is no other Name given under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven whereby we may be Saved,</hi> Acts 4. 12. The Name given him by the Angel at his Conception, carryed its import with it, St. Mat. 1. 21. <hi>Thou ſhalt call his Name Jeſus, for he ſhall ſave his People from their Sins.</hi> It is <hi>a Name</hi> at which all things bow <hi>both in Heaven and Earth:</hi> It ſpeaks Reconcilation on Earth, and Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in Heaven, and miſerable are their hopes that are founded on any other, tho' they be the Friends of God, tho' the Favourites of the Court of Heaven, yet if no Man can Redeem his own Soul, much leſs anothers; and in Reſpect of Redemption, and Eternal Salvation, we may ſay of them as <hi>Job</hi> of his Friends, <hi>Miſerable Comforters are they all.</hi> Neither Angels, nor Saints are appointed to be Mediators; neither the one nor the other ſhed their Blood to Redeem us; nor if they had,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95677:9"/> was it a valuable Price, or ſufficient Compenſation, and ſo could not plead in the Merits of it before God on our behalf: But he did both, he dyed to make an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement for us, and he ever lives to intercede in the Merits and Vertue of that propitiation, and there is no other way of approaching the Throne of Gods mercy, but through this ſatisfaction made to his Juſtice, no coming unto God but by him.</p>
            <p>But then that he may be able <hi>to ſave us to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt,</hi> we muſt come to God, <hi>i. e.</hi> (I have ſaid) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent our ſelves to God by Faith in him, as he himſelf explaines it, 1 Joh. 6. 35. <hi>He that cometh to me, ſhall never Hunger; he that believeth on me, ſhall never Thirſt;</hi> the one is Exegetical of the other. As under the Law, he that had Sinned was directed by God to go to the Prieſt, that he might make an Atonement for him by Sacrifice, ſo muſt we betake our ſelves to Chriſt our great High Prieſt, that by him we may have an Acceſs unto the Father, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 18. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the word denotes <hi>a Leading by the Hand:</hi> If we make our Application to him he will conduct us, and preſent us to his Father. The Faith that will ſave us, is ſuch a powerful perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the Soul as brings us to Chriſt; it brings us to a ſenſe of our need of him, and repreſents him alſo as infinitely deſirable, and worthy of all Acceptation. For deſire is the Flight of the Soul, and Faith gives it Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſets it on wing, and then becomes ſaving, when it carrys us out after him, and brings us home to him.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:95677:10"/>
            <p> This then is coming to Chriſt, and to God by him, when we are ſo firmly perſwaded that he is a Saviour <hi>able to ſave to the uttermoſt,</hi> that we commit our ſelves to him in holy Obedience and Well-doing, and truſt him with the Salvation of them in relyance on his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and in confidence of his Interceſſion.</p>
            <p>But I muſt leave this pleaſant Theme, a Subject too Copious for the Limits of my Time, or your Patience, and too Pregnant with Inſtructions to be applyed in all the Severals of it. I ſhall mention <hi>but One or Two</hi> of its moſt uſeful, and not leaſt ſeaſonable <hi>Corollaries,</hi> and ſo haſten to what muſt not be forgotten, and will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your Attention.</p>
            <p>You have heard what Chriſt has already done, what he is yet doing that he may be able <hi>to ſave to the uttermoſt:</hi> And what can more naturally reſult from thence, than,</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>The Encouragement that Sinners have to come to God by Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Second, <hi>The Comfort and Aſſurance they ſhall find in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyance on him for Salvation.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>The Encouragement that Sinners have to come to God by Christ.</hi> On God's part, we have the Declaration of his readineſs to be reconciled: On Chriſt's part, we have the voluntarineſs of his undertaking, and his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of the whole Work of our Salvation, he has ſuffered, and he has done every thing that was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to bring us to Glory: So that well might the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95677:10"/> call it a <hi>faithful Saying and worthy of all Acceptation, that Chriſt</hi> Jeſus <hi>came into the World to ſave Sinners,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 15. for what can God himſelf do more for man? Or, What can man do leſs than cloſe with ſo gracious an Offer? Who would not be glad to hear of a Saviour? Who would refuſe to come to ſuch a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, in whom nothing is wanting that may allay a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Fears, and encourage his Hopes? The very Name of an <hi>Advocate</hi> ſpeaks Courage to a guilty Criminal; but how ſhould we be encouraged to come to ſuch an Advocate as cannot be miſtaken in his Plea, nor fail in his Interceſſion? Weigh but St. <hi>John</hi>'s Character of him as ſuch, and then tell me whether you want any thing to enliven your Faith, or encourage your Dependance on him? <hi>We have,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>an Advocate with the Father,</hi> Jeſus <hi>Chriſt the Righteous.</hi> Every part of the Deſcription is an Argument for our Faith, and Ground of our Aſſurance. I can but point at the Chief: He's an <hi>Advocate,</hi> and ſo is to allege for the Juſtification of his Client; and you know we are juſtified by the Faith of him. He's to appear in our ſtead; and you have heard he ever lives to that purpoſe now, <hi>to appear in the Preſence of God for us,</hi> Heb. 9. 24. He's <hi>an Advocate with the Father;</hi> and that gives greater Encouragement ſtill; for that ſpeaks his <hi>Relation to the Judge,</hi> and we need not doubt of the Judges Favour, when we have his Son to ſpeak for us: It ſhews that he's <hi>appointed by the Judge;</hi> and, <hi>If God be for us, who can be againſt us?</hi> Rom. 8. 31. It intimates our <hi>Relation to him and the Judge;</hi> for being with the Father, and being our Elder Brother, he has
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95677:11"/> made him alſo our Father, as he himſelf ſaid, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. 26. <hi>I go to my Father and your Father, to my God and your God.</hi> Further, <hi>He's a Righteous Advocate; Righteous in himſelf,</hi> without Spot or Blemiſh, and ſo alone fit to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake for the Unrighteous: Righteous <hi>in his Plea,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving payd the Debt we owed, and laid down a Valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Compenſation for the Purchaſe he made; and he's <hi>Righteous to us,</hi> viz. In applying to us all the Benefits of his undertaking for us, ſo that if we perform what he requires from us, we may in Juſtice expect what he has promiſed us; which made St. <hi>John</hi> ſay, <hi>If we confeſs our Sins, He is Faithful and Juſt to forgive us our Sins.</hi> So that here <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> kiſs each other, and if either can invite, or both can perſwade, we have in ſuch an <hi>Advocate</hi> all that can encourage us to come to God by him, all that can facilitate our Hopes, and evidence the Aſſurance of Salvation through him.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>The Comfort and Satisfaction that is found in a firm relyance on him for Salvation.</hi> When a Soul upon theſe powerful Encouragements has embraced him for a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and caſt the Anchor of all its Hopes on him, how ſecurely does it ride amidſt all the Waves and Storms that may ariſe to ſhake its Faith, and endanger its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy? What a Calm does it feel in its ſelf amidſt the Aſſaults of Diſtruſt, and the threatning Tempeſt of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, whilſt it Eyes that Harbour of Safety, whereinto the Captain of its Salvation is already entred, and there waits to receive thoſe that follow him? How does it triumph in the APOSTLES unſhaken Confidence,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95677:11"/> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 33, 34. <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the Charge of God's Elect? It is God that juſtifieth. Who is he that condemneth? It is Chriſt that dyed, yea rather that is riſen again</hi> (and as a further Ground of Safety, and ſure Comfort too) <hi>who is even at the Right Hand of God, who alſo maketh Interceſſion for us.</hi> With this it repells all the Alarms of Fear and Deſpondence: In this it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyces over all Tribulations: With this it eludes the Snares of Temptations: With this it quenches all the fiery Darts of the Devil; and by this it triumphs o're the Fears of Death, <hi>(which ſpeaks Terror indeed to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but not to Grace)</hi> and looking on it as an Enemy already vanquiſhed by its Saviour, doubts not but thro' him alſo to obtain the Victory over it.</p>
            <p>Now what more pleaſant and rejoycing, than ſuch a Life of Faith? What more ſatisfactory than ſuch Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances at the Apprehenſions of Death? Certainly, did we know how to value both, it would quicken us to a watchful Endeavour after ſo happy an Attainment. Could we rightly eſtimate the Worth of our Saviours Interceſſion, it would captivate our Thoughts with ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing Delight, and reliſh in our Meditations of it, and kindle in our Minds the Warmth of Holy Joy and Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the Contemplation of it, and endear that part of our Saviour's Undertaking to our Choyceſt Thoughts and Affections, as a lively Faith does every thing that belongs to him, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> obſerves, 1 <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 7. <hi>To them that believe He is precious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have good reaſon to think that it had this influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on the well compoſed mind of <hi>this Vertuous Lady,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:95677:12"/> ſince the Remark ſhe left on it for this Occaſion, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed the impreſſion it had made on her <hi>Faith,</hi> and gave Evidence of the <hi>Hope</hi> She had here Treaſured up, and is now arrived at the end of the one, and the Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the other, Faith being become Viſion, and Hope Tranſlated into a feeling ſenſe of the Vertue of <hi>Her</hi> ever-living Saviours interceſſion, which <hi>She</hi> now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds in Ecſtaſyes of joy, and Tranſports of never end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pleaſure.</p>
            <p>But I muſt not dwell longer on theſe Pleaſant Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſince both the Occaſion Adminiſters Matter for more penſive thoughts, and Duty as well as Cuſtom Obliges us to pay, what is juſtly due to the Memory of that <hi>Right Honourable Perſon,</hi> whom Providence has made the Subject of our preſent grief and loſs. Of whom I am ſenſible it is very eaſy to ſay much, but withall very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to ſay all: And therefore if I preſent you with an imperfect draught (as <hi>Apelles</hi> is ſaid to have drawn <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus, Imagine luſcâ,</hi> half fac'd) I know that many that hear me can ſupply the <hi>Character</hi> out of their own knowledge, and make up what your <hi>Orator</hi> is Conſcious he muſt leave very defective.</p>
            <p>I will not detain you with an account of Her <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Parentage, the Quality of her Relations,</hi> or <hi>the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of</hi> Her <hi>Fortune,</hi> ſince her Perſonal Worth was a far richer Dowry, and her Commendable Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the beſt Monuments of her Praiſe.</p>
            <p>Her <hi>Temper</hi> was ſteady and even, equal to the very beſt, and Superior to moſt of her Sex, which if more Rare to be met with, is more highly to be valued when
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95677:12"/> found in the <hi>weaker Sex.</hi> An exact Harmony, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual proportion of the Elements, Naturaliſts ſay muſt Concurr to a fine, and even Temperament of Body: And in the Temper of Her mind there ſeem'd ſo juſt a proportion of thoſe diſpoſitions, which Embeliſh and Adorn Humane Nature, as rendred it an exact Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, fitly dispos'd for the impreſſions of Moral Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the higher improvements of Religious Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
            <p>This Evenneſs of Temper was manifeſt in the <hi>Calmneſs of her Spirit,</hi> not eaſily ruffled by Paſſion, nor diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd by Provocation. They muſt have known her long, that could ſay they had once ſeen Her in Paſſion, and not oftner out of Humour: And if She was once ſeen to be Angry, it was when the Provocation was too great to be put up without Reſentment, and was onely an Occaſion to manifeſt, that She was Liable to paſſions no leſs then others, but was better able to govern them than moſt.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Excellent diſpoſition of Nature,</hi> happily improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Advantages of Education, Years, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, made Her a ſingular Bleſſing to that <hi>Honourable Family,</hi> into which She Match'd; and to which She be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo endear'd in all the ſeveral Relations to it, of a <hi>Vertuous and Religious Conſort,</hi> of a <hi>tender and Indulgent Mother,</hi> of a <hi>kind and moſt Affectionate Relation,</hi> of a <hi>Loving Miſtreſs,</hi> dear to her Servants, and eaſy to all Her Family, that each of them think they juſtly reckon themſelves to have the greateſt loſs, and I think it hard to Name any Reſpect in which it is not ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:95677:13"/>
            <p> Her <hi>prudent Management of the Affairs of Her houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> was Accompanied with a watchful Care of, and Regard to, the good of Her <hi>Family,</hi> thinking Her ſelf E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually concern'd in the Morals of her Servants, as in diſcharging the duty of their places; and if at any time there was juſt cauſe, was an impartial Reprover of their Immoralities, yet with a Tenderneſs to their good, which ſhe took her ſelf to be always concern'd in, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing a diſlike of their Vices by Her endeavours for their Amendment.</p>
            <p>The <hi>great Care of Her domeſtick Affairs,</hi> was ſeen in being extended even to the ſmalleſt matters, which ſhe did not judge below Her inſpection, that She might not ſeem Unconcern'd in any thing, that might tend to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and good management. And the ſucceſs of it was ſo viſible in the whole Deportment of a well<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Regulated Houſe, as perhaps Created Envy in ſome, but Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in all, and may deſerve to be imitated, where it cannot be equall'd, muchleſs out-done, it being hard to ſay, whether it redounded more to <hi>Her Honour,</hi> or the <hi>ſatisfaction of others,</hi> and muſt be left undetermined whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was greater, the Plenty and Variety, or the Choice and Neatneſs of Her Entertainments.</p>
            <p>Amongſt other Concerns of Her Family, <hi>Her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> had not the leaſt of Her Care, as well as the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſhare in Her Affection; Her ſelf taking the pains of teaching them all to Read, and with the knowledge of Letters, inſtilling into them the early inſtructions of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and ſolid grounds of Religion, which even Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are Capable of remembring, and which if due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95677:13"/> Cultivated, they never forget all their life after.</p>
            <p>Her <hi>Reſpect to Her Lords Relations</hi> deſerv'd a better Name than Kindneſs, being a Sincere Affection and Real Love, manifeſt on all Occaſions, expreſt in all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of an endear'd Friendſhip.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dutifulneſs</hi> and <hi>Obedient Regard,</hi> where with She Honoured Her Father-in-Law, the Late <hi>Lord Delamere,</hi> gave Her the ſame place in his Affections, which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Challenges to the Iſſue of our own Bowels, and met with the equal Regard it Merited, and indeed could not fail to find in the excellent and ſweet Diſpoſition of that <hi>Honourable Lord, viz.</hi> a reſpect that wants <hi>a proper name</hi> to expreſs it.</p>
            <p>To the late <hi>Lady Dowager</hi> ſhe paid the Duty of a <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and Expreſs'd the Affection due to a <hi>Mother;</hi> then eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeen when Her Fatal Indiſpoſition began to betray her danger, and call'd for the Preſence and Comfort of Her dear Relations; how paſſionately did She receive the Summons? How ſollicitouſly did ſhe ſpeed to Her Succour, maugre the intemperance of the ſeaſon, and the darkneſs of the Night, even to the hazard of Her Health, which ſhe could ſooner venture than Conceal her filial Duty and Tenderneſs.</p>
            <p>To her <hi>Lord's Collateral Relations,</hi> ſhe was not more <hi>a Siſter</hi> than <hi>a Mother,</hi> nor leſs Lamented by them who beſt knew how to Value Her.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:95677:14"/>
            <p> To her <hi>Lord himſelf,</hi> ſhe was every thing that could En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dear her to him, <hi>Faithful</hi> and <hi>Obedient, Obliging</hi> &amp; <hi>Obſervant,</hi> not Curious to Gratify Her own Humour, but to comply with his, ſtudying wholly what might make for his <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, advantage,</hi> or <hi>conveniency.</hi> In all his Troubles and Dangers ſhe was ſtill an equal <hi>ſharer,</hi> and help'd to make them ſeem leſs to him, by bearing ſo great a part of the burden her ſelf. Yet in the midſt of her Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Affection (I may add too, Affliction) for him, ſhe retain'd that prudence and ſteadineſs of mind which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded comfort to him, and ſupport to them both. Her <hi>Tryals</hi> in that kind were very ſevere, yet born with a maſculine Vigour, and ſingular Diſcretion; and when ſhe muſt either be divorced from the Society of her <hi>dear Lord,</hi> or be made cloſe Priſoner with him, ſhe begg'd for a Voluntary Confinement, to the loſs of her <hi>Liberty,</hi> and apparent hazard of her <hi>Health.</hi> And after that ſtorm was happily blown over, and new dangers threatned him abroad, and her ſelf, with all that was near and dear to her at home, with what Courage and Patience ſhe weathered thoſe <hi>gathered clouds,</hi> I need not here Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, where 'tis ſo well known. But what will not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal Love and Duty go through, 'twas that gave life and ſupport to Her Spirit; 'twas that leſſened the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes ſhe ſhar'd in, and made them more eaſy at once to her ſelf, and her <hi>Honourable Conſort,</hi> who made the happineſs Mutual in Reciprocal Kindneſs, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of Endear'd love and Tenderneſs.</p>
            <p>But neither theſe Accidental Cares, nor the more Conſtant Concerns of Her Family, made her forget
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95677:14"/> or neglect her more <hi>important duty to God,</hi> 'twas <hi>his</hi> Favour ſhe depended on for a <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> and rightly judg'd <hi>Religion</hi> the means to obtain both, and made the practice of the duties of it, the great evidence of Her Title to it; being frequent in her <hi>private devotions,</hi> and conſtant in <hi>publick,</hi> in both ſerious and regular, without deſign or Affectation. Let <hi>this place</hi> ſpeak her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Attendance on the publick Ordinances, and her timely approach to Gods houſe, and the Decency of her Worſhip: An Example that wants imitation here, and deſerves to be Copied from ſo fair an Original.</p>
            <p>What <hi>ſhe learnt in Gods houſe, ſhe carryed home to her own,</hi> and <hi>Digeſted in her private Retirements;</hi> being through Her own induſtrious Piety, Excellently furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Choiceſt Subjects for Holy Thoughts, and Refined Meditations: For ſhe had the <hi>Pſalms</hi> by heart, than which, there cannot be higher Strains of Devotion, nor more Heavenly Raptures for the Soul to take its Flight in. Beſides theſe, ſhe had ſome ſelect portions, and places of Scripture, which ſhe made her <hi>Familiars,</hi> and endear'd to her thoughts by dayly Meditation, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt writ them with her own Hands, in a Book made and kept for that <hi>purpoſe,</hi> repeating them over e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very night, as ſhe did alſo in her laſt ſickneſs; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, <hi>this of my Text,</hi> which ſhe had ſet a mark upon in the Margin with theſe words, <hi>my Funeral Text,</hi> and I queſtion not had a more lively impreſſion on her <hi>mind</hi> of the comfortable import of it.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:95677:15"/>
            <p> Her <hi>Charity</hi> muſt not be forgot <hi>(the ſureſt Evidence of ſincere Devotion, and beſt Expreſſion of Religion)</hi> which was not publiſhed with the <hi>Sound of the Trumpet,</hi> done with Noiſe and Oſtentation, but rather by her Saviour's Direction, <hi>ſo as her Left Hand ſcarce knew what her Right Hand did;</hi> giving without asking, and ſending where it was not look'd for; finding out Objects of Charity where Modeſty conceal'd them, and making the Wants of others, not their Importunity, the Ground of her Liberality, <hi>feeding the Hungry, clothing the Naked, ſupplying the Neceſſities of the Indigent, adminiſtring not only Food but Phyſick,</hi> and all by ſo many various ways, in ſuch ſeaſonable Methods, as I am no more able to reckon up, than imitate.</p>
            <p>Yet her <hi>Alms</hi> were but a <hi>Moiety</hi> of her Charity, which was much more large and extenſive, <hi>(as it cannot fail to be where it flows from a true Charitable Diſpoſition)</hi> and diffus'd it ſelf through all the effects of Kindneſs and good Nature, which She had an Opportunity to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, or a fit Object to confer on.</p>
            <p>Her <hi>Courteous Mein,</hi> and <hi>Winning Affability,</hi> has an Atteſtation ſo general, as needs nothing more than the bare Mention of it; but muſt not here be omitted, leſt I ſeem to forget <hi>my ſelf,</hi> and wrong my <hi>Brethren of the Clergy,</hi> in not acknowledging the great Civility and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect She ever pay'd to our <hi>Function,</hi> which will remain amongſt us a laſting Monument of Her Honour.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:95677:15"/>
            <p> I muſt haſten to the laſt Stage of Her Life, and firſt Date of our Grief and Loſs, <hi>that Fatal Period,</hi> to which the Strength of Nature, and Flower of Age, and all the Arts of Phyſick were forc'd to yield, and which we had not met this day to Lament, if either the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Deſires of a Sorrowful Husband, or the innocent Sighs of Dear Children, or the Mournful Requeſts of Affectionate Relations, or the Tears of Her Family, or the Cryes of the Neighbourhood, or the Pathetick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Wiſhes of all good People, could have prevail'd for a Reſpite. But She more chearfully read the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Death in her ſelf,</hi> and prepar'd to Meet the <hi>King of Terrours</hi> without Fear and Amazement, or the Convulſions of Impatience; praying oft and ardently her ſelf, and calling on all about her to joyn with Her; lifting up Eyes ſtedfaſt in Faith, and joyful through Hope, till She breath'd out a Soul already on Wing towards the Regions of Bliſs, the Centre of all Her Hopes, the Sum of all Her Deſires and Prayers.</p>
            <p>I ſhall Conclude the Character in the <hi>Queen of Sheba's</hi> Words, (when ſhe found the Glory of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Court ſo far exceed the Fame that went of it) <hi>That half hath not been ſpoken.</hi> Had She liv'd to perfect what She had ſo well begun, She had left the World a lively Draught of real Worth and Goodneſs, and built Her own <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument</hi> in a Pattern worthy of Imitation: And we muſt reckon it our own Loſs, not Hers, that She was ſo ſoon call'd off the Stage, and muſt draw the <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> o're that part of the <hi>Scene</hi> which we can now on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſh She had ſtayd to finiſh.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:95677:16"/>
            <p> May the <hi>Copy</hi> She left be the Tranſcript of Her <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity:</hi> May her Piety and Vertuous Endowments be hereditary in that <hi>Right Honourable Family,</hi> and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to the Succeſſion of many Generations: May Providence repair the Breach that is there made, and reſtore the Voice of Joy and Gladneſs <hi>to the Houſe of Mourning:</hi> May his all-wiſe Diſpenſations leave on <hi>us all</hi> the Impreſſions of Wiſdom and thoughtful Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that the <hi>Living may lay it to Heart,</hi> that we who ſurvive, may with Patience and Well-doing, wait for our approaching Change, and improve this ſad <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer</hi> of our Frailty, to the Inſtructions of Duty and ſeaſonable Meditation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:95677:16"/>
            <p>FORMS of Private Devotion for every Day in the Week, in a Method agreeable to the Liturgy; with Occaſional Prayers, and an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the Holy Communion, and for the Time of Sickneſs. Humbly recommended to all the Pious and Devout Members of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the Queen at <hi>White-Hall, February</hi> the Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, 1690/1. By <hi>Henry Dove,</hi> D. D. Chaplain to Their Majeſties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roman</hi> Forgeries in the Councils, during the firſt Four Centuries, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with an Appendix, concerning the Forgeries and Errors in the Annals of <hi>Baronius.</hi> By <hi>Thomas Comber,</hi> D. D. Precentor of <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Scholaſtical Hiſtory of the Primitive and general Uſe of Liturgies in the Chriſtian Church; together with an Anſwer to Mr. <hi>David Clark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s late Diſcourſe concerning Liturgies; in Two Parts, in <hi>Octavo.</hi> By the ſame Hand.</p>
            <p>Seaſonable Reflections on a late Pamphlet, Entituled, <hi>A Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience ſince the Reformation;</hi> wherein the true Nation of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Obedience is ſettled and ſecured from the Malicious Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ill deſigning Men.</p>
            <p>The Golden Rule, or the Royal Law of Equity explained By <hi>J. Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>The Frauds of the Romiſh Prieſts and Monks ſet forth in Eight LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERS; lately written by a Gentleman in his Journey into <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A late Letter concerning the Proceedings in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſufferings of the Epiſcopal Clergy there, in <hi>Quarto,</hi> price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Political Arithmetick, or a Diſcourſe concerning the Extent and Value of Lands, People, Buildings; Husbandry, Manufacture, Commerce, Fiſhery, Artizans, Seamen, Soldiers; Publick Revenues, Intereſt, Taxes, Superlucration, Regiſtries, Banks; Valuation of Men, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of Seamen, of Militia's, Harbors, Situation, Shipping, Power at Sea, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As the ſame relates to every Country in general; but more particularly to the Territories of His Majeſty of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and his Neighbors of <hi>Holland, Zealand,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> by Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Petty,</hi> late Fellow of the <hi>Royal Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their preſent Majeſties Government proved to be throughly ſettled, and that we may ſubmit to it, without aſſerting the Principles of Mr. <hi>Hobbs;</hi> ſhewing alſo, That Allegiance was not due to the Uſurpers, after the late Civil War; occaſion'd by ſome late Pamphlets againſt the Reverend Dr. <hi>Sherlock.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
